<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-21T02:15:31+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tamzin atkins</title><subtitle>A collection of topics I'm passionate about and lessons learned.</subtitle><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Toolkit 02</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/toolkit/2021/02/26/toolkit-february-2021.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toolkit 02" /><published>2021-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/toolkit/2021/02/26/toolkit-february-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/toolkit/2021/02/26/toolkit-february-2021.html">&lt;p&gt;My yearly theme for 2021 is &lt;a href=&quot;https://tamzinatkins.com/self-improvement/2021/01/01/year-of-intention.html&quot;&gt;Intention&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I’m sharing three resources that I’ve found to be helpful while I strive to focus on what matters to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;book&quot;&gt;Book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make Time, by Jake Knapp and John Zeratsky&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jakeknapp.com/make-time&quot;&gt;Make Time&lt;/a&gt; provides many strategies for making small changes in our daily lives to help us live our lives the way we really want to, and how to achieve more of what we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Headspace Guide to Meditation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/title/81280926&quot;&gt;Headspace Guide to Meditation&lt;/a&gt; is presented as an series on Netflix. Andy Puddicombe, co-founder of Headspace, introduces the what, how, and why of meditation, and guides the viewer through an approximate 10 minute meditation each episode. Headspace also has an app where subscribers gain access to guided meditations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;app&quot;&gt;App&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When possible, I like to start with free apps when trying something new. &lt;a href=&quot;https://insighttimer.com/&quot;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; is a free app with a library of guided meditations along with calm and soothing options to help you fall asleep. I’ve been listening to guided meditations around letting go of stress and anxiety, and affirmations for self-confidence. It’s also been helpful when falling asleep, switching between music and spoken word.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="toolkit" /><summary type="html">My yearly theme for 2021 is Intention. Today, I’m sharing three resources that I’ve found to be helpful while I strive to focus on what matters to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sprint</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/book%20notes/2021/02/19/sprint-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sprint" /><published>2021-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/book%20notes/2021/02/19/sprint-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/book%20notes/2021/02/19/sprint-review.html">&lt;p&gt;As I became more and more interested in product development, I found the book &lt;em&gt;Sprint&lt;/em&gt;, by Jake Knapp, John Zeratsky, and Braden Kowitz. I am familiar with agile practices, and understand the practice of two week software sprints to work towards a customer software release, but the one week design sprint was new to me. &lt;em&gt;Sprint&lt;/em&gt; details a process to find answers quickly to - typically - business case questions, aiming to provide a successful prototype quickly. I’ve identified six categories regarding what I learned and points that stood out to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;golden-nuggets&quot;&gt;Golden Nuggets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several points in the book allowed me to reflect on having the proper mindset, and planning my day in order to be productive. Distractions are everywhere, and providing a bit of strutcure can help mitigate those urges to detract from the task at hand. It takes approximately “23 minutes for distracted workers to return to the task at hand” (39). For me, my distractions include a pressure to reply to a recent Slack message immediately, beginning to work on a more “fun” task than the one I really should be working on, and checking email too often. All of this task fragmentation impedes my ability to get focused and find my &lt;a href=&quot;https://tamzinatkins.com/productivity/2020/11/27/finding-your-flow-state.html&quot;&gt;flow state&lt;/a&gt;. I’m the most productive in my flow state, and it’s easier to find that flow state when I’m motivated. As the authors write, “you probably feel the most productive when you’re doing” something “you’re especially good at” (218). It’s so important to me to enjoy what I do, so that I’m all the more motivated to get tasks done, and enjoy the process of working towards completion. Having “six working hours in the typical sprint day” is a reminder to myself to prioritize quality over quantity when it comes to work (39). It’s a reminder to work with myself and listen to my body. If I’m working for 20 minutes, but all I’m doing is metaphorically banging my head against the wall, am I really working? I’m certainly not making progress on the task I had laid out before me. I’m tired or struggling to find motivation, and now may be stressed, having seemingly wasted the last 20 minutes. Take a break from that task and revisit it later. The authors suggest to “run a sprint anytime you’re not sure what to do, struggling to get started, or dealing with a high stakes decision” (230).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sprint-focus&quot;&gt;Sprint Focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you begin, it’s helpful to understand the end goal you’re working towards. As the authors put it, “start at the end” (55). I really like the mindset of turning the problem into questions - putting the issue at hand in a more positive light - moving beyond stating that there is a problem, and following up with being open to accepting possible solutions. This is imperative to my work on a daily basis, and likely that of many others. These questions are called your sprtint questions. What questions do you “want to answer in this sprint?” (57). “Turning these potential problems into questions make them easier to track - and easier to answer with sketches, prototypes, and tests. It also creates a subtle shift from uncertainty (which is uncomfortable) to curiosity (which is exciting)” (57-58). After brainstorming sprint questions, you’ll move on to “choose a target for your sprint” (84). With a week where you have your team’s undivided attention because all other meetings have been erased from the calendar, what do you want to build a prorotype for and test at the end of the week, knowing you have a group of people’s precious time for 5 days? After you’ve selected a target, review the list of sprint questions; “one or more should line up with the target” (88). This question will be your guiding light, as it’s the question you’re looking to answer by the end of the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facilitator&quot;&gt;Facilitator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a project manager, I took a keen interest in the facilitator role, which comes with its own ABC slogan: “always be capturing” - a quote by Josh Porter (89). (In sales, ABC refers to always be closing.) A great way to capture ideas is to press your team further, even when the answer may seem obvious. Pretend you’re an outsider, who isn’t familiar with any of the topics the team is familiar with (90). This runs in the same vein as the Five Whys technique when pressing to find root cause or explore underlying cause-and-effect relationships. Put simply, ask “why?” multiple times to dig deeper into what the underlying issue may be. In addition to asking why, “ask open-ended questions” and steer away from any leading questions (212). While extracting thoughts from people’s heads, it’s also the facilitator’s role to ensure the group stays on track, focused on the agreed upon task at hand. In terms of a design sprint, prevent new ideas creeping in during middle of sprint. When someone brings up something that detracts from the design sprint task at hand, acknolwedge it as a valid point, take note, but table for now - perhaps this will be something that gets discussed in the coming weeks, but for now, it’s time to focus on the design sprint (159). This acknolwedgement, taking note, and tabling discussions is also an important practice in meetings. You show respect to the individual who introudced it, and as it’s deemed appropriate, schedule another meeting - dedicated time to discuss this new item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decision-making&quot;&gt;Decision Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parkinson’s Law states “work expands so as to fill the time available for its completion,” as stated by Cyril Northcote Parkinson himself in an essay entitled &lt;em&gt;Parkinson’s Law&lt;/em&gt;, published in The Economist in 1955. When you must identify an issue, build a prototype, and test it all in one week, quickly making decisions is crucial. One way to cut down on the decision making feedback loop is to restructure how solutions are identified and evaluated. The authors suggest to share all possible solutions up front, instead of intiating discussions surrounding a few, and identifying other ideas as a result of earlier discussions. This way, all cards are layed out on the table from the beginning, and all solutions are critiqued together, allowing a decision to be made more quickly (128). The authors then outline how to go about making the decision to identify which components of various solutions the team should move forward with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Art museum: Put the solution sketches on the wall with masking tape.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heat map: Look at all the solutions in silence, and use dot stickers to mark interesting parts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Speed critique: Quickly discuss the highlights of each solution, and use sticky notes to capture big ideas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Straw poll: Each person chooses one solution, and votes for it with a dot sticker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supervote: The Decider makes the final decision, with - you guessed it - more stickers.&lt;/em&gt; (131)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The points that stand out to me about this five-step process are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The speed critique for each solutions lasts for just three minutes (136)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Decider (example: product manager/owner) must make honest decisions - it’s up to them to take in the feedback from the group, and decide if they agree with the consensus or not (140)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test early. Whether it turns out to be a dud or spectacular, “it’s better to find out early” (168). This reminds me of one of my favorite quotes from the author Jen Sincero: “Deciding is freedom. Indecision is torture.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices&quot;&gt;Best Practices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set the team up for success by building your line-up. An important common trait to have amongst members of the sprint team is that they have expertise. They have unique backgrounds that enable them to be invaluable members of the team (33).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As much as the team is chomping at the bit, excited to execute solutions, ensure the design sprint’s priorities are sorted first - lay out the plan, before jumping in (54-55).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The knowledge about the challenge you’re tackling is distributed amongst those familiar with it. Gather information from indiviudals who are included in the sprint team, along with individuals who are not included, but also have insights into the challenge at hand (68).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work alone, together:&lt;/em&gt; have individual brainstorms in the same room. Give individuals time to think and brainstorm ideas without being interrupted by one another (107).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be optimistic when prototyping. You’ll find “&lt;em&gt;some way&lt;/em&gt; to prototype and test your product” (169).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reactions are much more valuable than feedback during a test. Pay close attention to how test subjects interact with the prototype (170).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When something appears to not be successful, it may be because “there’s [a] gap between the vision and the customer,” to quote Joe Gebbia, co-founder of Airbnb. Remedy that by talking to people (211).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timetimer.com/&quot;&gt;Time Timer&lt;/a&gt;: a visual timer that shows the passage of time with a red disk (47)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Map it out: include the key players and major steps of the story or sequence of events (65)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How Might We (HMW) exercise: convert something interesting you heard into a question; capture “a problem and convert it into an opportunity” (75, 78)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Storyboards: “use your storyboard to imagine your finished prototype, so you can spot problems and points of confusion before the prototype is built” (149)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Color coding: color code observations (green = positive, red = negative, black = neutral) (220)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="book notes" /><summary type="html">As I became more and more interested in product development, I found the book Sprint, by Jake Knapp, John Zeratsky, and Braden Kowitz. I am familiar with agile practices, and understand the practice of two week software sprints to work towards a customer software release, but the one week design sprint was new to me. Sprint details a process to find answers quickly to - typically - business case questions, aiming to provide a successful prototype quickly. I’ve identified six categories regarding what I learned and points that stood out to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Anatomy</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/career/2021/01/18/project-management-human-anatomy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Anatomy" /><published>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/career/2021/01/18/project-management-human-anatomy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/career/2021/01/18/project-management-human-anatomy.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to make the analogy that projects resemble the human body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body relies on multiple systems working in sync to remain functional. Projects are similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digestive-system&quot;&gt;Digestive System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digestive system represents the &lt;strong&gt;project life cycle&lt;/strong&gt;. Just like projects, the digestive system has a distinct beginning and end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Five Stages of the Digestive Project Life Cycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Mouth (Initiation)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;outline the purpose (ie: business case) and requirements of the project&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Stomach (Planning)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;define scope&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;define project management plan: schedule, milestones, and communication and risk management plans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;define roles and responsibilites&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Duodenum (Execution) &lt;em&gt;The duodenum is the first section of the small intestine, where stomach contents mix with digestive enzymes from the pancreas and bile from the liver&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;kick off meeting&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;assign resources&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;task assignments&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;set up tracking systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Small Intestine (Monitor and Control)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) to measure project performance - ensure the quality of deliverables&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adjust schedule and resources as applicable&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Large Intesting (Close)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;final project review&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lessons learned&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;skeletal-system&quot;&gt;Skeletal System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a project, the skeletal system is comprised of the &lt;strong&gt;team members&lt;/strong&gt; - the group building the deliverables. This core group has specific areas of expertise that enable them to execute on project activities, making them the foundation, or structure, of a project, much like a skeleton provides structure to a vertebrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nervous-system&quot;&gt;Nervous System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nervous system represents all &lt;strong&gt;stakeholders&lt;/strong&gt;, including the product owner or client, and their opinions on the project overall and specific activities. Stakeholders are anyone and everyone who is actively involved with the project and whose interests are impacted, positively or negatively, by the project. What messages are the nerves receiving? And how are those messages received by the brain (ultimate decision maker: product owner or client)? The nervous system is responsible for stimulating muscles - it’s important for the project manager to be assessing feedback from project stakeholders - is the project progressing satisfactorily for the stakeholders?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;muscular-system&quot;&gt;Muscular System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;project manager&lt;/strong&gt; is the muscular system - acting as the connective tissue to drive a successful project, empowering team members to be successful and work together. The project manager evaluates inputs from the stakeholders, or nervous system, and orchestrates the development team, or skeletal system, as applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;circulatory-system&quot;&gt;Circulatory System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circulatory system represents &lt;strong&gt;risks and issues&lt;/strong&gt;. I think of roadblocks as being similar to one’s circulation getting cut off. If there is a resource missing, it’s difficult for a team member to complete a task without a resource they were relying on. On the flip side, opportunities are similar to circulation being reintroduced to an extremity or other area in the body.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="career" /><summary type="html">I like to make the analogy that projects resemble the human body.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2021: The Year of Intention</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/self-improvement/2021/01/01/year-of-intention.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021: The Year of Intention" /><published>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/self-improvement/2021/01/01/year-of-intention</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/self-improvement/2021/01/01/year-of-intention.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m not making any New Year’s resolutions. Instead, I’ve decided to follow a yearly theme. Let me tell you more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-yearly-theme&quot;&gt;What is a yearly theme?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The yearly theme was introduced to me while listening to the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.relay.fm/cortex&quot;&gt;Cortex&lt;/a&gt;, hosted by CGP Grey and Myke Hurley. A yearly theme puts an emphasis on making forward progress - moving the needle from your current state towards where you want to be. And, themes are meant to be broad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are you looking to achieve? What do you want to focus on? What do you want to improve upon?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading this, I invite you to listen to the following Cortex Yearly Theme Episodes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.relay.fm/cortex/62&quot;&gt;#62: 2018 Yearly Themes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.relay.fm/cortex/79&quot;&gt;#79: 2019 Yearly Themes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.relay.fm/cortex/95&quot;&gt;#95: 2020 Yearly Themes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.relay.fm/cortex/110&quot;&gt;#110: 2021 Yearly Themes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-i-prefer-a-yearly-theme&quot;&gt;Why do I prefer a yearly theme?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I’m a strong believer that &lt;strong&gt;better is good&lt;/strong&gt;. Progress is success. I’m often my harshest critic, and I’m working on keeping a positive mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What little steps or actions can you take every single day to move your needle?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a year like 2020, we know all too well that a year may not go as we had planned. I appreciate the malleability of a yearly theme, and sprinkle in some measurable goals along the way. I want to feel content with what I accomplish each day, and be happy with how I spent my time that day. It’s not about getting everything done, rather, getting everything I want to get done, done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-intention&quot;&gt;Why intention?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be intentional in making progress, I must focus on myself, and my needle, and not compare myself to others. I ended 2020 listening to Jen Sincero’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/You-Are-Badass%C2%AE-Doubting-Greatness/dp/0762447699/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;sr=&quot;&gt;You are a Badass: How to Stop Doubting Your Greatness and Start Living an Awesome Life&lt;/a&gt; audiobook for a nice momentum boost, and I began 2021 watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/title/81074662?mc_cid=10dd42fde5&amp;amp;mc_eid=4a862fbef5&quot;&gt;The Minimalists: Less Is Now&lt;/a&gt; on Netflix. &lt;em&gt;Less is Now&lt;/em&gt; is a continuation of the story told in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/title/80114460?s=a&amp;amp;trkid=13747225&amp;amp;t=cp&quot;&gt;Minimalism&lt;/a&gt; (also on Netflix), and in part, discusses the importance of looking within - &lt;em&gt;what is your definition of success and happiness?&lt;/em&gt; Because others will have their own, and different criteria. Comparing ourselves to others is overwhelming, and unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also important to remember that personal growth is only natural. We’ll meet our own goals and seek out new ones. We evolve, and so will our goals and definitions of success and happiness. I want to be mindful that I’m changing me for me, and not for impressing others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Less is Now&lt;/em&gt; asks the viewer to reflect on this question: &lt;em&gt;what brings value to your life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Side note: It’s no coincidence that I enjoy Matt D’Avella’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/blackboxfilmcompany&quot;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;. Matt is the director of both &lt;em&gt;Minimalism&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Minimalists: Less Is Now&lt;/em&gt;. I also invite you to check out Matt’s content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-want-to-be-more-intentional&quot;&gt;How I want to be more intentional&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-and-writing&quot;&gt;Reading and Writing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started this blog late in 2020, and I want to continue posting on a regular basis. It’s been very rewarding finding creative outlets for myself, where in the past, most of my outlets have entailed physical exercise, including running, hiking, and snowboarding. I still love hiking and snowboarding, and I now go on walks instead of runs. It’s something new - something to revisit. Growing up, my least favorite school subjects were reading and writing, but now, when I have the freedom to choose what I read and write, it’s been refreshing to partake in these activities - I don’t carry that dread in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to journal every week to spend time reflecting and exploring thoughts. What I’m grateful for. Recounting a transformative experience. Or diving deeper into a conversation I had earlier with a friend. Some of these topics will be shared here on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coloring&quot;&gt;Coloring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing within the creativity realm, I enjoy coloring in coloring books, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.johannabasford.com/book/secret-garden/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. This is another activity I started in 2020 and one I want to bring into 2021 and beyond. I find it to be relaxing, and a nice way to wind down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-nothing&quot;&gt;Do nothing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to do nothing. Intentionally. Doing nothing is a struggle, so I want to integrate meditation into my daily life. To be more present, and less distracted. With my busy brain, I’m often asking myself, “how is this productive?” Read: what chore should I be doing? What space could I tidy? Guess what. Rest is important. I want to enjoy more small moments each day, and pace myself for a long and marvelous life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;limit-my-scrolling&quot;&gt;Limit my scrolling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly the news. Don’t get me wrong, I think it’s important to be an informed citizen of the world. But I don’t need to check it every 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it! I’m looking forward to reflecting on this down the road. Happy New Year, everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="self-improvement" /><summary type="html">I’m not making any New Year’s resolutions. Instead, I’ve decided to follow a yearly theme. Let me tell you more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DIY Christmas Decorations 2020</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/projects/2020/12/16/christmas-decor-2020.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DIY Christmas Decorations 2020" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/projects/2020/12/16/christmas-decor-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/projects/2020/12/16/christmas-decor-2020.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-final2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;christmas-light-garland&quot;&gt;Christmas Light Garland&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created my own Christmas decorations that will last for years to come, deciding to make a garland of oversized Christmas lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-decisions&quot;&gt;Design Decisions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simulate an illumination effect with glitter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seal in the glitter so it doesn’t rub off everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;Materials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x 2ft x 4ft piece of 1/4in plywood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint (acrylic paint by craft smart in white, black, metallic silver, red, yellow, green, turquoise)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Super Gloss Mod Podge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glitter (chunky glitter by Recollections in red, lemon, pine, and teal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-paint.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-modpodge-glitter.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shaper Origin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/4in upcut bit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/8in upcut bit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engraving bit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint brushes of varying sizes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint trays&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plastic spoon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2mm twine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noun Project - &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenounproject.com/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy using icons that are available on Noun Project, because they can be downloaded as an SVG file, the file format Shaper Origin accepts for cutting out designs. I purchased and used this &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenounproject.com/search/?q=christmas+light&amp;amp;i=253466&quot;&gt;icon&lt;/a&gt; by icon 54. I wanted to enjoy these as soon as possible, so I did not edit the design file to simplify my cutting experience. Instead, I played routing hopscotch - jumping around between multiple cut paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas_light_svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cutting-workflow&quot;&gt;Cutting Workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Map a 1/4in square grid using Shaper Origin so the center line running the length of the bulb was lined up on the grid (this will help with a later cutting step).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Import SVG file, and scale up to be 5 inches tall, using the scaling option on Shaper Origin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place SVG file so that center line running the length of the bulb is on a grid line (see Step 1).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using on-tool CAD capabilities on Shaper Origin, place a 4mm diameter circle towards the end of the cap - this will be the stringing hole, as seen below, denoted as the light green circle on Origin’s screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-string-hole.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy the 5in Christmas light and the 4mm circle to make 28 Christmas lights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut out one row of Christmas lights at a time, a strategy I used to balance 1) minimizing the number of times bits are getting exchanged, and 2) being mindful to ensure enough Shaper Tape is undisturbed and can be recognized by Origin.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cut the outline of the Christmas light with a 1/4in upcut bit, cutting along the outside of outermost cap and bulb cut paths. Start at the right side of the cap (when looking at the bulb hanging downwards with the cap on top), cut around the cap counterclockwise, then select the outermost line of the bulb, and cut around the bulb, until you reach where you started cutting the cap. I ignored some of the cut paths - the illumination marks and inner paths of the bulb - for this project.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Engrave the top of the bulb to separate it from the bulb’s cap, using the outside cut path type.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cut the inside path of the 4mm circle with a 1/8in upcut bit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-cutouts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After all cutting is complete, sand the edges of each Christmas light cutout.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint the top surface with white paint to serve as a primer - two to three coats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint the sides black - three coats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint the bulb cap silver cap, also painting the engraved line visual separator - three coats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint equal number of each colored bulb - three coats. In my case, I painted seven of each of the four colors - red, yellow, green, and blue, painting one color at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-painted.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;12&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add glitter to bulb - I did these steps one color at a time, as to minimize cross contamination of the different glitter colors. My workbench was large enough for me to set completed bulbs off to the side so I could complete each step for each color in rapid succession.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Paint over the colored bulbs with Super Gloss Mod Podge, ensuring the entire bulb surface is covered.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Over a small plate to catch the glitter, heavily sprinkle the matching colored glitter.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Let sit for a few minutes before lifting up Christmas lights to remove any loose glitter.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Set aside for four hours, or overnight.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ensure all loose glitter has been removed by gently hitting the side of each cutout gently on the workbench.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spoon out Mod Podge into a tray, and work from, as to not get any glitter from the paint brush into the Mod Podge container. Paint over the glitter with Super Gloss Mod Podge.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Allow to sit overnight. Super Gloss Mod Podge’s label states that this compound cures in 4 weeks. I’ve been successful in completing this project the next day, without issues when handling my cutouts and will wait to pack these decorations up at least until the cure date.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-sample.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;13&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;String together! I chose 2mm twine, approximately 14cm spacing between Christmas lights, and the color order of: yellow, red, blue, green.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-final2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am proud of the result, and I’m considering other designs, like gingerbread people and snow people, for future Christmas garland projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was very happy with how well the Super Gloss Mod Podge sealed in the glitter, and still allows the glitter to shine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next time, I’ll edit the SVG file so that my cutting workflow is more straightforward and I don’t need to remember to jump cutting paths. Because when I forgot to jump cutting paths, this happened:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/christmas-light-mistake.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting in the flow</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/productivity/2020/11/27/finding-your-flow-state.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting in the flow" /><published>2020-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/productivity/2020/11/27/finding-your-flow-state</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/productivity/2020/11/27/finding-your-flow-state.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-flow-state&quot;&gt;What is a flow state?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A flow state is a mental state in which an individual is focused whole-heartedly in an activity - those times where you look up at the clock, time has flown by, and you pat yourself on the back for being productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-into-a-flow-state&quot;&gt;How to get into a flow state&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found through exploration that the following six strategies help me get out of a rut and into my flow state. I use these strategies for work and personal tasks alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-focus-on-a-single-task&quot;&gt;1. Focus on a single task&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t listen to conversations or music with words because my brain is trying to capture the message that’s being communicated. This means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no podcasts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no Netflix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want my brain power to be focused at the task at hand, so that when I’ve completed a task or several, I can reward myself with a break by watching or listening to something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-tasking and being able to juggle shifting priorities at work are two different things. You can be aware of the current status of three different projects by tackling one task at a time, where you determine the order in which tasks need to be completed. I’m never in two meetings at the same time - because how productive would that be? I think of tasks as meetings with myself, where my expectation for myself is that that I’ll be focusing on a given task at a given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-listen-to-instrumental-music&quot;&gt;2. Listen to instrumental music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have three working modes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “I gotta find my groove” warm-up mode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The relaxed “Cool, I’m making progress” mode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The very amped “BOOYAH! LET’S DO THIS” mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes, regardless of my work mode, I find it helpful to listen to music. Be kind to your ears and find a comfortable set of headphones that fit your ears and head - don’t sabotage yourself by being uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m in my warm-up and super amped working modes, I enjoy listening to pump-up music, mostly electronic music. When I’m warming up, it helps me get into the groove, and when I’m pumped, it keeps my energy high. On the other hand, when I’m relaxed and motivated, I’m typically listening to either jazz or Lo-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-tidy-your-workstation&quot;&gt;3. Tidy your workstation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easier for me to get my work done when a chore like cleaning up a cluttered desk isn’t staring right back at me. I won’t necessarily really clean up right then and there when I want to start working, but organize papers into piles based on what I need access to at the moment to complete the task I’m working on. I suggest either putting items back in their proper place immediately, or for the time being, move it so it’s not distracting - let it be the floor or in another room - and put it away later. I don’t care - I’m not your mom. Sometimes the chore of properly putting items a way is a disguise for procrastination. For this reason, you may prefer to sort through your papers later in the day or when I want to take a break - when peak brain function isn’t required. The task at hand &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; requires more brain power than it will take for me to go through the papers and truly clear the clutter - I’ll do that when I want to take a break from my task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-move-around-and-map-it-out&quot;&gt;4. Move around and map it out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love brainstorming and planning on a white board or using Post-It Notes arranged on brown kraft paper I have attached to a flat surface - let it be a wall, door, or table. I find it incredibly satisfying to write everything down and see it all at once - plus, it’s an opportunity to step away from my desk. For example, I enjoy the tactile interactions of moving around Post-It Notes on a large sheet of kraft paper when I’m project planning and building a dependency diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I’m done with the planning activity, I’ll take a photo of it to reference when I’m back at my desk and type up what I mapped out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-take-a-break&quot;&gt;5. Take a break&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you feel yourself slipping out of your flow state, getting tired, or otherwise feel like you’re fighting yourself - I recommend taking a break. Instead of hitting your head against the wall for 20 minutes, trying to think of that missing piece, or trying to figure out where to begin, do something else - work on a different task, go for a walk and listen to a podcast, or fold the laundry. Shower thoughts (epiphanies that occur when our brain is relaxed) occur in lots of places, and having one come to mind can be the ignition you need when you sit back down to be focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been the most challenging practice to implement personally, but - oh man - it really works for me. I too often would say to myself, “Just think a bit harder, and you’ll get past this mental block,” or when I lacked motivation, “Come on, just do it so you can check it off the list.” I’m now much better at stepping away from an unproductive situation, to allow myself to come back with a better mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-schedule-focus-time&quot;&gt;6. Schedule focus time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one afternoon each week blocked out on my work calendar as an event called “no meetings.” This is time I reserve for myself, ensuring I have several consecutive hours each week where I’m not interrupted by my coworkers. You schedule meetings with your coworkers, do the same thing for yourself! Don’t try to schedule all of your focus time - I certainly don’t. Everything can’t be scheduled - much like how it’s very likely that you probably have spontaneous conversations with your coworkers outside of scheduled meetings, productive periods often happen organically.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">What is a flow state?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toolkit 01</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/toolkit/2020/11/26/toolkit-november-2020.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toolkit 01" /><published>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/toolkit/2020/11/26/toolkit-november-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/toolkit/2020/11/26/toolkit-november-2020.html">&lt;p&gt;You are your best advocate - yes, you! Self-confidence is so important. I’d like to share some resources of various mediums that help me remain encouraged and motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fearless, by MALINDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My go-to pump-up song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/watch?v=tdykGWbIck0&amp;amp;ab_channel=MALINDA&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;podcasts&quot;&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Intentional Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This podcast really helps me self-reflect. Host Tanya Dalton discusses topics surrounding career and productivity, and themes each season, comprised of approximately 13 episodes. Learn more about the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://tanyadalton.com/podcast&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. For example, the theme for Season 15, which wrapped up recently, was &lt;em&gt;strategies for success&lt;/em&gt;. Two episodes I really enjoyed from Season 15 were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;192: How to Stop Hesitating and Start Getting What You Want&lt;/strong&gt;: As I said earlier, you are your best advocate!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;193: Embracing Your Expertise&lt;/strong&gt;: Many women are hesitant to own the title of “expert,” and Dalton explains why and how we should own it. In addition, here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/354649&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to the article Dalton wrote for Entrepreneur that she refers to in this episode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Her Stem Story&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This podcast focuses on stories surrounding STEM careers. Host Prasha Dutra shares her experience along with those of her guests to empower others. Learn more about the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://herstemstory.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;film&quot;&gt;Film&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enola Holmes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this adventurous film, which is available on Netflix. It follows Enola Holmes, the younger sister of Sherlock Holmes, as she searches for her mother, with the backdrop of women’s suffrage and social reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;networking&quot;&gt;Networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Girl Geek X&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girl Geek X hosts events for women in tech, of all disciplines, providing an incredibly positive and empowering environment for listening to female speakers and connecting with others. I really enjoy attending these events. Check out the Girl Geek X website &lt;a href=&quot;https://girlgeek.io/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="toolkit" /><summary type="html">You are your best advocate - yes, you! Self-confidence is so important. I’d like to share some resources of various mediums that help me remain encouraged and motivated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Career advice for students… and everyone else</title><link href="http://tamzinatkins.com/career/2020/11/12/advice-for-students.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Career advice for students… and everyone else" /><published>2020-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://tamzinatkins.com/career/2020/11/12/advice-for-students</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://tamzinatkins.com/career/2020/11/12/advice-for-students.html">&lt;p&gt;I majored in mechanical engineering for my undergraduate degree. The following are lessons learned from my experience in school and my first few years in industry after graduation. I’ve tried to generalize my thoughts with the hope that people of various disciplines walk away with tips they can pursue further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learn-what-you-enjoy-and-what-you-dont&quot;&gt;Learn what you enjoy and what you don’t&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning what you don’t enjoy doing is equally, if not more important than knowing what you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; enjoy doing. I found it easier to drill into what I enjoyed doing, by excluding what I did not enjoy. Early on, I only had vague terms for what I enjoyed doing, and I was having a hard time drilling down into what exactly I did enjoy. Listing out tasks and responsibilities I preferred to not do helped me identify the parts I did enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sign up for classes that peak your interest but are outside of your graduation requirements. Alternatively, or perhaps to help you determine which class you may want to take, check out sites that provide free access to online courses, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/&quot;&gt;edX&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ocw.mit.edu/index.htm&quot;&gt;MIT OpenCourseWare&lt;/a&gt;. These resources come without the commitment of paying for a class, or the stress of needing to decide whether or not to drop a class before the deadline passes. Use internships as part of your exploration, and this exploration will continue throughout your career once you enter the workforce - you’ll continue to learn what parts of each job you enjoy and do more of, along with parts you’d like to step away from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do side projects - these can be as small or as large as you want, and include these in a portfolio of your work along with class projects. Show that you’re a passionate learner, and present projects along with the skills you used and developed - it shows that you’re motivated and itching to learn. I approach side projects in one of two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowing what skill you want to practice and develop a project around that, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a project you’d like to accomplish, or a problem you’d like to solve, and discover what skills are required, and get exposed to them and practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduation, don’t be afraid of changing jobs - you’ll likely change jobs every 2-5 years - this is what I’m surrounded by in the San Francisco Bay Area. You won’t be doing the same thing for the next 20 years - don’t be afraid of getting stuck, and work to ensure you don’t get stuck somewhere you don’t want to be. Continue learning and be your own advocate. Someone’s recent advice to me included: &lt;strong&gt;do what interests you now&lt;/strong&gt;. As in, at this moment, what do you enjoy doing? When this answer changes, that’s when you transition and pivot, but don’t try to predict what your career trajectory should look like. Your education is merely a starting point, and it doesn’t define your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News flash: you won’t learn everything you need to know in school. I’ve learned so much on the job, and I don’t see that changing. Continue learning after you’ve graduated - it’s good for your brain, I’m sure you’ll discover new things you’d like to learn about, and it’s important to stay relevant. This next suggestion draws from my experience as an individual who earned a degree in mechanical engineering: Take computer science classes as a mechanical engineering student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Example 1: You’re conducting reliability testing on a prototype that includes motors. It would be valuable to have some coding experience, so that you can have more control and ownership over how you test and move the motors, without needing assistance from a software engineer on your team - it allows you to be more autonomous, not needing to wait for a software engineer to assist you when you get stuck.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Suggestion: learn &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arduino.cc/&quot;&gt;Arduino&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source electronic prototyping platform&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Example 2: You’re gathering a bunch of data, and want to be able to analyze the data more quickly, and run many queries - you’re running up against the limits of Excel and Google Sheets.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Suggestion: learn the programming language &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, and after you understand the basics, explore the data analysis library called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-typical-jobs-in-a-field-of-study&quot;&gt;What are typical jobs in a field of study?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest looking up job descriptions for roles in various industries within your discipline of interest. Look up open opportunities on LinkedIn or any other job board. Take a look at the job description (what you’ll be doing day-to-day) as well as the job requirements (education and experience). What skills and responsibilities appeal to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a few roles that leverage a background in mechanical engineering include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mechanical engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mechanical design engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;product design engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aerospace engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;controls engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;systems engineer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;am-i-happy-with-my-decision-to-major-in-mechanical-engineering&quot;&gt;Am I happy with my decision to major in mechanical engineering?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes - although while I was a student, I couldn’t tell you what I wanted to do with my degree - I knew I enjoyed math and science. While working in industry, I’ve discovered that I really enjoy project management and data analysis. As I write this, my current job title is &lt;em&gt;Technical Project Manager&lt;/em&gt;, and after reflecting on my time in college, I noticed my role combines some of my favorite parts of school and my interests in general: I enjoy being organized and designing processes to allow myself and others to follow the same procedures to work better together (let it be project planning, or documentation), and I enjoy being a team leader, rallying people together. I have a track record of this while I was in school - both in class projects and working as a TA for several of my professors, serving as a resource to students. In my current role, I get to interface with technical coworkers of various engineering backgrounds to solve engineering problems. I leverage my degree as my foundation of technical understanding, to be an educated individual in the conversation, able to provide my own thoughts and understand my coworkers, and continue learning when discussing issues with other engineers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tamzin Atkins</name></author><category term="career" /><summary type="html">I majored in mechanical engineering for my undergraduate degree. The following are lessons learned from my experience in school and my first few years in industry after graduation. I’ve tried to generalize my thoughts with the hope that people of various disciplines walk away with tips they can pursue further.</summary></entry></feed>